In the sixth century BC, China was a maze
of competing states engaged in constant
warfare with each other. Strangely, it was
in this chaotic violence that Confucianism,
a quasi-religious philosophical system emphasising
harmony and balance, emerged. But Confucius was no
saint either. He was deeply involved with several
of the warring Chinese states and regularly fell
out with those around him. At least that’s the
image presented of him in the ancient sources.
Who was Confucius and how was his philosophical
system shaped by the chaos of sixth-century BC
China? This is the story of Confucius, the
most influential man in Chinese history.
The man known to history as Confucius
is traditionally said to have been born
on the 28th of September 551 BC in the
village of Zou near the city of Qufu,
then the capital of the state of Lu in
eastern China. His birth name was Kong Qiu,
though most Chinese people know him as Kongzi or
“Master Kong.” Confucius is a Latinized name used
by the Western world and is based on the variant
of his name Kong-fu-zi or “Great Master Kong.”
It was coined by Jesuit missionaries in the
sixteenth century after European contact with
China became more extensive following the
Portuguese arrival to the Far East.
While Confucius’ legacy was cemented in
the centuries after his own lifetime,
as his sayings were collected and compiled
in a collection known as the Analects,
historians face considerable challenges in piecing
together a biography of the historical Confucius.
The earliest full account of his life is found
in the Shiji or Records of the Grand Historian,
the seminal work of Chinese historiography written
by the great Chinese historian Sima Qian over
three hundred years after Confucius’ death. While
the Shiji is considered a work of serious history,
by the time Sima Qian wrote it, several
generations of Confucius’ followers had already
embellished the biography of the great sage with
numerous legendary tales. Sima Qian may have
drawn on the Kongzi Jiayu, meaning the Sayings of
Confucius’ Family, which is understood to be based
on a text compiled by a descendant of Confucius
in the second century BC. According to this text,
Confucius’ father was Shuliang He, an official
in the state of Lu and a member of the Kong
clan. There was no clear distinction between civil
officials and military officers at this time, and
in around 563 BC Shuliang served in the Lu army
besieging the city of Biyang. He was among a group
of soldiers who stormed through the city’s open
gates, but soon noticed the entrance closing in
behind him and realised that his party had fallen
into the enemy’s trap. He demonstrated unusual
strength by holding the gate open for his men to
escape before retreating to safety himself.
By the time of this exploit, Shuliang
was already approaching his sixties.
He and his wife, Lady Shi, had nine children,
all daughters. Although Shuliang had a son from
a concubine named Kong Pi, the boy was apparently
disabled, which prevented him from carrying out
the appropriate ancestral rites after his father’s
death. With Lady Shi long past childbearing age,
Shuliang decided to seek another wife who could
bear him an heir, and approached a neighbour named
Yan who had three daughters of childbearing age.
As the young ladies listened to their father extol
the virtues of Shuliang, despite his advanced age,
the elder two remained silent, while the youngest,
Yan Zhengzai, remarked to her father that there
was no point in asking them their views on any
proposed marriage, since he had the authority to
decide. The teenage Zhengzai’s answer prompted
her father to marry her off to Shuliang, then in
his late sixties. The age difference between the
couple would have caused some scandal in itself,
and Sima Qian suggests that Confucius’ parents
were never actually officially married.
According to the traditional narrative,
Zhengzai did not expect Shuliang to live long and
went to pray at the nearby Mount Ni for the son
that he so desperately desired. She had a dream in
which she encountered a qilin, a legendary horned
creature likened to a unicorn, who informed her
that she would give birth to an “uncrowned king.”
While she was confused by the vision, her prayers
were answered in 551 BC, when she gave birth to a
son named Kong Qiu, the man who would come to
be known as Confucius. After coming of age,
he was given the courtesy name of Zhongni, which
is believed to mean “Second Son from Mount Ni.”
In the mid-sixth century BC, when Confucius was
allegedly born, China was already a relatively
mature civilisation with a population of up
to 50 million people. The country was formally
a kingdom ruled by the kings of Zhou from the
city of Luoyang in present-day Henan Province.
The Zhou Dynasty was established in the eleventh
century BC after overthrowing the Shang Dynasty,
the dominant power in the valley of the Yellow
River. To legitimise their rule, the Zhou kings
developed the concept of the Mandate of Heaven,
through which virtuous rulers were said to display
divine favour. The new regime argued that the
Shang had lost the Mandate of Heaven due to the
behaviour of the notoriously corrupt Di Xin,
the last Shang king, and that accordingly the
Zhou takeover was endorsed by Heaven. The newly
established dynasty maintained a feudal system and
appointed family members and prominent supporters
as dukes to help them govern the realm. As part
of this process, the duchy of Song was given to a
Shang prince who submitted to the new order. Zhou
founder King Wu hoped to pacify the spirits of the
Shang kings by allowing him to continue performing
the Shang ancestral rites. The Kong family claimed
to trace its ancestry to the dukes of Song,
and through them to the Shang kings. Over the
centuries, the duchies began acting independently
from their Zhou overlords and became major centres
of independent political power. With Zhou royal
authority already in decline, their capital,
Fenghao, near present-day Xi’an, was occupied
by Qiang tribesmen in 771 BC. The surviving royals
relocated to Luoyang, marking the beginning of the
Eastern Zhou Dynasty. The first three centuries of
the Eastern Zhou is also known as the Spring and
Autumn Period, named after the Spring and Autumn
Annals, the official chronicle of the State of
Lu covering the period from 722 to 481 BC, a work
traditionally attributed to Confucius. While the
Eastern Zhou kings held symbolic authority, their
political control was limited to the area around
Luoyang. This was an age of constant conflict
between these warring feudal states.
As the most influential thinker in Chinese
history, Confucius has been quoted in dozens of
Chinese classics dating from the fourth century BC
onwards. For much of Chinese history the Analects
have been regarded as the most authentic source
of his teachings. Known in Chinese as Lunyu or
‘selected sayings,’ they contain some 500 sayings
attributed to Confucius, each of which starts with
the phrase “The Master Says.” These are then
organised into 20 scrolls or chapters. It was
believed in ancient times that these sayings were
compiled by Confucius’ students after his death.
However, by the seventeenth century, the
inconsistencies and disorganised nature of
the text prompted scholars to formulate what is
called the “accretive theory,” which argues that
while some of the sayings can be traced back to
Confucius himself, the text was actually compiled
by early Confucianists over several generations,
with the earlier chapters considered the most
authentic. In a 1998 publication by the American
Sinologist, E. Bruce Brooks, and his wife,
Taeko Brooks, entitled The Original Analects:
Sayings of Confucius and His Successors, it was
argued that the received text was composed between
Confucius’ death in 479 BC and the conquest of
Lu in 249 BC. According to their theory, only
Chapter 4 can be attributed to Confucius himself,
while chapters 5 to 20 were added over
time. They consider chapters 1 to 3 to
be miscellaneous introductory material inserted
in several stages. A third group of scholars are
more sceptical still about the traditional view
and stress the differences between Confucius,
as he is presented in The Analects, and his
appearance in the work of Mengzi or Xunzi,
his most influential followers who lived in the
fourth and third centuries BC respectively. They
argue that the Analects, as we know them today,
were compiled at a single moment in time during
the Western Han Dynasty and are an amalgamation
of several early Confucian traditions. As early
as the third century BC, the pre-eminent Legalist
scholar, Han Feizi, observed that the Confucian
school had split into eight factions, each of
which claimed to teach the authentic Confucius.
Ultimately, it is almost impossible to know
anything with certainty about the historical
Confucius from the surviving ancient texts.
While dozens of ancient Chinese sources that
reference Confucius as an authority can be used
alongside The Analects to provide an account of
how Confucius’ teachings came to be understood
over time, any attempt to provide a coherent
biography of Confucius has to be based
on the traditional accounts in the Shiji,
the Kongzi Jiayu, and The Analects, while
acknowledging some of the more legendary
and fantastical elements. This is the approach
taken in numerous modern biographies of Confucius.
While Confucius claimed noble heritage, his
branch of the family had been reduced to
commoner status and had adopted the surname Kong.
His great-grandfather Kong Fangshu left the state
of Song to seek his fortune in the neighbouring
state of Lu, where he and his descendants
served as officials with minor noble rank. While
Confucius had been born into a respectable clan,
his prospects seemed bleak following the death of
his father when he was only three years old. While
Shuliang was buried at a site called Fangshan,
Confucius was unaware of its location. According
to Sima Qian, his mother did not inform him of
the grave-site, possibly because she had been
barred from the funeral by the Kong family. The
boy was therefore unable to perform the ancestral
rites to honour his father. Nevertheless, under
the guidance of his mother, he grew up with the
desire to venerate his late father, and as a
child he often played with bowls and plates and
pretended that they were sacrificial vessels.
There is no reliable account of Confucius’
appearance, though the Shiji claims that he
owed his name Qiu, meaning ‘hill’, to a bump
on the back of his head. As an adult, he is said
to have inherited his father’s towering physique,
being over two metres tall. While this is not
impossible, it was a common literary device
in ancient times to associate exaggerated
physical characteristics with supernatural
abilities. Confucian tradition holds that he
had an impoverished childhood, and a couple
of the sayings in Chapter 4 of The Analects imply
that Confucius had experienced adversity on more
than one occasion. If he and his mother had indeed
been ostracised from the rest of the Kong family,
particularly if his half-siblings remained
under the same roof, his childhood would not
have been one of great luxury. Nevertheless,
he appears to have received a good education
in line with his family’s status. Children of the
scholar-official class that Confucius belonged to
were expected to be proficient in the “six
accomplishments”: propriety or adherence
to social norms of conduct, music, archery,
charioteering, calligraphy, and mathematics.
Several of the sayings attributed to Confucius
in The Analects attest to his love for learning.
Indeed, the first saying of Chapter 1 begins: “The
Master said, To learn and in due time rehearse it:
is this not also pleasurable?” While learning
texts by recitation has been a staple of Chinese
education for over 2,000 years, for Confucius
education was not only about accumulating
knowledge but the application of learning to guide
personal behaviour in private and public life.
For much of Chinese history, scholar-officials
supported their arguments by quoting from classic
texts in debate. Confucius’ disciples claimed
that their master placed particular emphasis
on the study of ritual, music, poetry and
history as guidance for virtuous behaviour
for scholar-officials serving the state.
According to a passage in Chapter 2 of The
Analects, Confucius began to really dedicate
himself to learning at the age of 15. He was in
his late teens or early twenties when his mother
died. Sometime later he was informed about the
site of his father’s tomb and he reburied his
parents in a new grave. When Confucius was 19,
he married a woman from the Qiguan clan in the
state of Song. Lady Qiguan soon gave birth to a
son named Kong Li with the courtesy name Boyu.
The boy’s personal name Li means “carp,” while
his courtesy name may be translated as “Elder
Fish.” The Kongzi Jiayu explains that Duke
Zhao of Lu gifted Confucius and his wife a carp
upon the birth of their son, an honour that the
father commemorated by then naming the child
after the fish. While Confucius and his wife
had at least two more daughters, their marriage
was traditionally said to have been unhappy. A
saying from Chapter 17 of The Analects quotes the
sage: “Women and common people are hard to handle.
If you let them get close, they take advantage;
if you keep them at a distance, they resent it.”
Confucius allegedly preferred discoursing with
his male disciples over the company of his wife,
who is barely mentioned in the records. The
anecdote around the naming of Confucius’ son
suggests that despite his impoverished upbringing,
he was known to the ruling elite of the state
of Lu as a young adult. Even so, he was not
universally accepted by the Lu aristocracy.
The government was then controlled by the Ji,,
Meng, and Shu clans, each descended from a former
duke. When Confucius was still a teenager, he
was denied entry to a feast hosted by the Ji clan
on the grounds that he was not a gentleman.
The incident fuelled his resentment against
the Ji clan, and he criticised them for being
wealthy and having little regard for ritual.
According to Confucius’ great disciple Mengzi,
better known in the West as Mencius, he began
his career in his early twenties as a low-level
bureaucrat responsible for grain supplies. While
he dutifully performed his tasks, he acquired a
reputation as an authority on ritual and attracted
a small group of students. Among his earliest and
most accomplished students was a teenager named
Zilu, who often appears in dialogue with Confucius
in The Analects. Confucius continued learning from
others, demonstrating great curiosity when
questioning visiting dignitaries. By his
early thirties, he had established himself as a
teacher and as an unofficial advisor at the Lu
court. Shortly before his death, the head of
the Meng clan had recognised his talents and
encouraged his sons to seek instruction in ritual
from Confucius. His knowledge of protocol saw him
accompany Lu officials travelling on trade or
diplomatic business. On a visit to the Zhou
capital of Luoyang, Confucius paid close attention
to the design and layout of the city’s principal
religious sites and was impressed by how the Zhou
royal family venerated its ancestors. Confucius
held the early Zhou rulers in high regard,
particularly King Wen, whose reforms laid the
foundations for the conquest of Shang by his son,
King Wu. Confucius also lionised the Duke of Zhou,
who consolidated the kingdom’s control over
China as regent following the death of his
brother King Wu and dutifully stepped aside after
his nephew came of age. According to tradition,
it was in Luoyang that Confucius met Laozi
or the “Old Master”, the founder of Daoism,
who was then serving as the royal archivist at
court. Daoism or Taoism would go on to emphasise
the idea that people should live in harmony
with the Dao, the “right way.” The older man
warned the young Confucius that his interest
in ritual counted for little when contemporary
rulers carried out the ancient rites out of habit
rather than understanding, and that Confucius
would inevitably make powerful enemies at the
Lu court by insisting on proper behaviour.
Confucius was closely associated with Duke Zhao.
In 517 BC, when Confucius was in his mid-thirties,
the Duke’s attempt to arrest a member
of the Ji family for insulting him
triggered an uprising. The Meng and Shu clans
raised their armies and joined the rebels,
and Duke Zhao was defeated in battle and
forced to flee to the neighbouring State of Qi.
Confucius and his disciples followed the Duke into
exile. A famous anecdote from the Book of Rites,
a core Confucian text, describes Confucius’ party
passing Mount Tai when they encountered a woman
weeping endlessly next to a grave. The woman
explained that she was mourning her son, who
was killed by a tiger which had already claimed
the lives of her husband and father-in-law. When
Confucius asked her whether she considered living
somewhere without tigers, she replied that “There
is no tyranny here.” The astonished scholar turned
to his students and remarked, “Remember this,
my children, tyranny is fiercer than a tiger.”
Upon his arrival at the Qi court, Confucius
was impressed by its ritual and music, but was
critical about the abilities of its ministers.
He was welcomed by local scholars and sought
office from Duke Jing of Qi. While the Duke
respected Confucius and turned to him for
political advice, the Qi ministers regarded
him as an upstart who was after their jobs. When
the Duke considered disinheriting his eldest son,
Confucius remarked, “Let the lord be a lord,
the minister a minister, the father a father,
and the son a son.” Confucius was thus advising
the Duke not to arbitrarily change the succession
laws, while hinting that his ministers were
exceeding their responsibilities.
Duke Jing was sufficiently impressed by Confucius
to offer him a minor administrative post,
although this was opposed by his chief minister,
Yan Ying, who argued that the newcomer’s emphasis
on elaborate rituals would leave no time for
government business. Following this intervention,
Duke Jing withdrew his favour from Confucius, who
decided to return to Lu. Back in his home country,
Confucius was particularly critical of the conduct
of the Ji clan. Chapter 3 of The Analects quotes
Confucius’ condemnation of the extravagance of
ceremonies, which not only signalled pretensions
to royal privileges reserved for the king of
Zhou, but hinted at the misuse of state funds.
In Chapter 4 of The Analects, he says “Everyone
desires wealth and honour, but if he cannot do
so in accordance with his principles, he will
not abide in them. Everyone detests poverty and
lowliness, but if he cannot do so in accordance
with his principles, he will not avoid them.”
The passage is part of a group of sayings
stressing the importance of ren, the cardinal
Confucian virtue that does not have a singular
definition but is associated with benevolence,
trustworthiness, compassion, and empathy. In
the period that followed Confucius appears to
have focused his energies on his teaching.
Several of the dialogues in The Analects
show Confucius rebuking his students for
their failure to understand his teaching.
While Confucius claimed to be passing on
traditional wisdom rather than developing
radical new ideas, his own views evolved over
time, a factor that may have contributed to his
followers splitting into several factions
in the decades after his death.
Among the students of Confucius’ school was his
son Boyu, who was by now a young man in his early
twenties. He was not a particularly distinguished
student, and only makes a single appearance in the
Analects. Some of Confucius’ newer students
suspected their master was reserving special
knowledge for his favourite disciples. Chen Gang
approached Boyu and asked him whether he received
any special teaching from his father. Boyu
answered no, but noted that his father had advised
him to pay particular attention to the Book of
Songs and the Book of Rites. Alongside the Book of
History, the Book of Changes, and the Spring and
Autumn Annals, these texts were part of the Five
Confucian Classics which later became core texts
in Chinese civil service examinations. According
to Sima Qian, Confucius spent his time in the
political wilderness editing the Book of Songs,
the Book of History, the Book of Rites, and the
lost Book of Music. The first saying in Chapter
7 of The Analects has Confucius declaring “I
transmit and do not invent, trusting in and
loving the ancient ways.” Confucius did not claim
any originality but believed his role was to pass
on ancient wisdom that was being neglected
by his contemporaries in an age of political
disorder. His traditional biography suggests
that he made little progress towards this goal
during his lifetime, and modern scholars believe
that even his modest achievements in office were
exaggerated by later generations. The centrality
of Confucian thought in later Chinese culture
owes much to Confucius’ disciples. Sima Qian
names over 70 individuals in his list of
Confucius’ first-generation disciples. Of these,
the most famous was Yan Hui, a possible maternal
relative who joined his school as a young man
in the late 500s BC. Confucius said of him,
“I can talk all day with Yan Hui, and he never
disagrees with me, as if he were a fool. But
after he goes home, it is enough to observe his
conduct to realise that he is not stupid.”
Following the death of Duke Zhao around 510
BC, the aristocracy in Lu bypassed Duke Zhao’s
eldest son and instead elevated the late duke’s
younger brother to become Duke Ding. The new duke
was effectively a puppet of the aristocracy,
although by the end of the sixth century BC
the Ji clan’s power was itself usurped by its
leading retainers Yang Hu and Gongshan Buniu,
also known as Gongshan Furao. The latter had
risen in rebellion and seized the town of Fei
from the Ji clan. Confucius seriously considered
an offer to serve Gongshan, but his disciple Zilu
dissuaded him, noting that he would be abandoning
his principles by supporting a rebel. In 501 BC,
the two officials were defeated and forced into
exile while Duke Ding reasserted his authority
and assumed control of the government. With the
legitimate ruler back in charge, Confucius then
accepted an appointment as chief magistrate of the
remote town of Zhongdu. In his new administrative
capacity, Confucius continued to emphasise the
Book of Songs and the Book of Rites, which not
only laid down rules for proper behaviour but gave
practical advice about agricultural and economic
management. Under Confucius’ administration, these
codes of best practice became law. While later
scholars regard accounts of Confucius’ success
in office as attempts by later generations of
Confucians to promote their ideology by presenting
him as a man who gained official acceptance in his
own lifetime, Confucian tradition holds that his
administration was so successful that his policies
were emulated in towns across the state of Lu.
Confucius’ exploits attracted the attention of
Duke Ding, who soon appointed him as Assistant
Minister of Works. Among the several exchanges
between Confucius and Duke Ding cited in The
Analects, the Duke asks the sage if there is
one saying or principle that can guarantee
prosperity in a state. Confucius said there
was no single saying that could be so effective,
but quoted a maxim that “being a ruler is hard,
and ministers face many difficulties.” The
Duke then asked if there was a single saying
that would bring about the downfall of a state.
Confucius said again that it would take more than
a single sentence to do irreparable damage
to the state, but that the closest thing was
for a lord to think “the only good thing about
being in charge is that nobody opposes me.”
Sima Qian describes Confucius playing a key role
at a diplomatic conference between the rulers
of Lu and Qi in 500 BC. The countries had been
constantly at war, and Duke Jing of Qi invited his
Lu counterpart Duke Ding for negotiations at Jiagu
in Qi territory. Confucius accompanied Duke Ding
as head of the Lu ministerial delegation. Given
their historical rivalry and the fact that Qi
harboured political fugitives from Lu, including
the rebellious officials Yang Hu and Gongshan
Buniu, Confucius suspected that Duke Jing was
seeking to take advantage of Lu and had advised
his lord to have two senior military officials
in attendance, citing an ancient precedent. As
the two dukes met, Duke Jing authorised some of
his subjects to perform a war dance. Confucius
intervened and remarked that a “barbarian dance”
with weapons breached protocol and claimed that
it demonstrated that Qi was not behaving in
good faith. The Duke of Qi was chastened,
and over the course of subsequent negotiations
agreed to cede a number of disputed towns that
Qi had seized from Lu by force. Confucius’
success in resolving the dispute in Lu’s
favour without any bloodshed increased his
influence at court, and within a few years
he was appointed Minister of Justice. Sima Qian
claims that within three months of taking office,
Confucius had eliminated corruption by
market traders, the streets were safe,
and visitors from near and far could conduct
their business without any hindrance.
Sima Qian also credits Confucius with a major
reform to strengthen Duke Ding’s authority.
For centuries, the Lu aristocracy had been able
to challenge ducal power by maintaining private
armies and securing themselves within their
walled towns. Confucius therefore proposed to
pull down these fortifications and disarm the
private armies, leaving the Duke at a distinct
advantage as the ruler of the only fortified
city. Duke Ding approved Confucius’ suggestions,
and Confucius secured the appointment of his
disciple Zilu as the steward of the Ji clan to
implement the policy. While the Shu clan quickly
complied, some of the Ji retainers put up armed
resistance and marched on the capital of Qufu.
The Duke’s troops emerged victorious and proceeded
to pull down the walls of the Ji capital, but Lu
forces were less successful in besieging the head
of the Meng clan, who sheltered behind his town
walls and withstood several assaults, even after
Duke Ding assumed personal command. Confucius’
policy of centralising power also caused great
anxiety in the state of Qi. With the Duke in
control of the men and resources of all three
clans, Qi would be vulnerable to invasion by Lu.
While Duke Jing was prepared to withdraw to more
defensible frontiers and cede further territory to
Lu, one of the Qi officials suggested a scheme to
undermine Confucius’ policies. The tale goes that
after Duke Jing began neglecting his venerable
duties and was tempted into taking gifts of fine
horses and dancing girls, Confucius quietly left
the court. When a messenger from the Ji clan
caught up with him and asked him to return,
he rebuked the Lu elites for carousing with
dancing girls and continued on his journey.
According to tradition, Confucius spent the
decade after his departure from Lu wandering
throughout China seeking a virtuous lord
to serve and living a peripatetic life,
only to be disappointed on every occasion that he
believed he might have found a lord worthy of his
service. Sima Qian claims that Confucius travelled
to eight other feudal states seeking office before
he returned home. The convoluted itinerary of his
wanderings in Sima Qian’s writings was possibly
an attempt to make Confucius’ message seem more
universally Chinese in light of his otherwise
strong ties to the state of Lu in eastern
China. The first stop in Confucius’ traditional
itinerary was the state of Wei to the west, where
Zilu’s brother-in-law held office. Confucius had
previously been critical of the morals at the Wei
court, but he was welcomed by Duke Ling of Wei,
who appointed him as an advisor and awarded him
the same salary he received in Lu. Confucius
was targeted by critics who denounced him to
Duke Ling, and while he maintained the duke’s
favour he chose to leave the Wei court after ten
months. He travelled south through a region that
bordered his native Lu and was soon forced to
turn back when his entourage was attacked by a
mob that had mistaken him for his rival Yang Hu,
whose armies had previously sacked the region.
He was detained for ten days until his beloved
disciple Yan Hui came to rescue him. Back in Wei,
Duke Ling had married Lady Nanzi, a woman of
loose morals who was known for conducting an
incestuous affair with her brother. Confucius
was appalled by the developments at the Wei
court but was obliged to call on the duchess after
receiving a message from her reminding him that
it was his duty to answer her summons. Although
Zilu was scandalised by his master’s decision,
Confucius argued that duty overrode his
moral objections in this instance.
In the same year, 494 BC, Duke Ding of Lu
died and was succeeded by his son, Duke Ai.
While the new duke hoped to restore Confucius to
office, other ministers complained that Confucius
had embarrassed the court in earlier times with
what they claimed was his excessive moralising.
They were fearful that he would humiliate them
again if given the opportunity. As a compromise,
the Lu court offered the post to one of Confucius’
disciples, and the master reluctantly dispatched
his student Ran Qiu with instructions to lobby
for his own return to office. Sima Qian goes on to
describe a series of episodes in which Confucius
and his itinerant scholars came into difficulty.
For instance, while on the way to the state of
Zheng, Confucius lost his way and was separated
from his followers for a while. Eventually he made
his way south to the state of Chen, where he would
stay for three years. He was welcomed by Duke Min,
who sought to test his knowledge by presenting him
with a dead falcon which had been shot by a stone
arrow. This weapon was unusual in the Chinese
heartland, but Confucius explained that stone
arrows were used by the Sushen, a tribal people
who lived in present-day Manchuria. Confucius
noted that the Sushen presented arrows as tribute
to King Wu of Zhou. Some of these arrows formed
part of the dowry of the king’s eldest daughter,
whose husband was the founding Duke of Chen.
Duke Min checked his armoury and discovered
more stone arrows of the same type.
Confucius spent three years in Chen, but since the
state was at war with three of its neighbours, he
decided to leave. He eventually returned to Wei,
which was in the midst of a succession struggle
after the death of Duke Ling in 493 BC.
The late Duke’s eldest son Prince Kuaikui had
been exiled for plotting against his stepmother,
and the succession passed to the latter’s son, who
succeeded his grandfather, Duke Chu. Upon hearing
of his son’s succession, Kuaikui returned to Wei
and sought to claim the ducal throne for himself.
Kuaikui appealed to Confucius for aid, but the
sage remained neutral. While Confucius’ disciple
Zilu entered Duke Chu’s service, the Master
himself abandoned his political ambitions and
returned to his studies. Confucius continued
to receive visitors asking him for advice,
but he was unconcerned by then about having
a powerful patron. His presence in Wei had
always been insecure, and when he received
a message from his disciple Ran Qiu that the
ruling elite was prepared to allow him to return
to Lu, Confucius seized the opportunity and left
in 484 BC. While he was widely revered
by his compatriots upon his homecoming,
Confucius was in his late sixties and was bitterly
disappointed about the lost opportunity during his
lengthy exile. Although he welcomed the fact that
his disciple Ran Qiu controlled the government,
he was disappointed that he often disregarded his
advice. According to tradition, Confucius’ major
preoccupation during this final period of his
life was the compilation of the Spring and Autumn
Annals, an official history of his homeland which
he supposedly intended as a guide for lords and
their ministers. While the style is relatively
dry, Confucius, if indeed he was the author,
which is highly debatable, did offer his opinions
in places about the actions of past generations.
In addition to the history he was writing,
Confucius also spent this period editing the
Yijing or Book of Changes, an ancient divination
text that involved 64 hexagrams which court
diviners had to interpret. Although it has since
lost its political significance, the “I Ching”
has attracted attention in the Western world
as a classic of ancient Chinese wisdom.
Tradition holds that Duke Ai occasionally turned
to Confucius for advice in the sage’s final years.
In 481 BC, for instance, Confucius was summoned
to help identify a strange animal that had been
captured. He recognised it as the qilin,
the same horned creature that had appeared
to his mother shortly before his birth. Just as
the qilin heralded the birth of a great sage,
it also foretold the death of one, and Confucius
wept at the thought of his imminent demise.
Confucius soon fell seriously ill but recovered.
In the meantime, he became a grandfather after his
daughter-in-law gave birth to a son named Kong Ji,
courtesy name Zisi, who would in time continue the
family line and become a respected philosopher in
the tradition of his grandfather. Within a year,
the child’s father, Boyu, died at around 50 years
of age. Confucius presided over a modest funeral
for his son. The great sage would suffer further
bereavement after learning of the demise of Zilu,
who had been mortally wounded while protecting
Duke Chu from a successful coup by the latter’s
father, who assumed power as Duke Zhuang
II. Confucius had recently been at odds
with Zilu’s conduct as a minister in Wei but was
nevertheless saddened by the news of his death.
However, his grief paled in comparison
to the news that his favourite student,
Yan Hui, had died in his early thirties. Confucius
hoped that the younger man would succeed him at
the head of his academy. He bitterly mourned his
loss and Confucius followed him to the grave soon
afterwards, dying, according to the ancient
sources, in spring 479 BC at the age of 72.
After Confucius’ death, his school disbanded
and his disciples went their separate ways. The
dispersal of the Confucians and the emergence of
different schools of his followers cemented his
legacy as China’s most influential philosopher.
The general narrative of his life as a combination
of a quasi-religious philosopher who moved between
serving various lords and wandering China with his
followers developed in the centuries after his
own lifetime, though how accurate any of these
biographical details are, is difficult to
say and has led to extensive debate amongst
Confucian scholars. The growth of his legacy
was facilitated by political developments in
the centuries after his death. The Eastern Zhou
declined further during the Warring States period
as ambitious dukes began challenging the Luoyang
court by calling themselves kings. From among
the seven major warring states that emerged in
the late fifth century BC, the State of Qin in
the west would eventually conquer all its rivals
and complete the unification of China in 221 BC.
While the policies of Emperor Qin Shi Huang were
anathema to the Confucians, China remained united
under the succeeding Han Dynasty, the emperors of
which claimed to be guided by Confucian values in
contrast to Qin Shi Huang. Confucianism
moved to the heart of Chinese government
in the succeeding centuries, particularly after
the imperial civil service examination system,
which was heavily influenced by Confucian ideals,
was expanded during the Song Dynasty between the
tenth and thirteenth centuries AD. China’s
position as the leading East Asian power also
enabled the spread of Confucianism to Korea and
Japan. It was only at the start of the twentieth
century that the civil service examinations
and their Confucian elements were abolished. In
spite of the anti-Confucianist campaigns during
the Communist Cultural Revolution, Confucius’
influence in China and beyond remains strong.
What do you think of Confucius? Was he a
frustrated scholar-official who sought to improve
standards of government administration in an age
of misrule, or was he a reactionary who
wanted to create an unrealistic utopia?
Please let us know in the comment section and in
the meantime, thank you very much for watching.